Inventory of the Igor Aleksandrovich Dashkevich papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Igor Aleksandrovich Dashkevich papers
1956-2008
2013C8
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes (2.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, samizdat publications, and photographs relating to political dissent in the Soviet Union and to the establishment of independent labor organizations in post-Soviet Russia.
Dashkevich, Igor Aleksandrovich, 1956-2008.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Igor Aleksandrovich Dashkevich, a Russian dissident, journalist, and political activist from Saint Petersburg, was involved in establishing independent trade unions and independent political and trade union publications during and immediately after the collapse of the Soviet system.
As a representative of the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) in Saint Petersburg from 1993 to 1996, Dashkevich played an important role in uniting independent labor unions in the mid-1990s: so many had sprung up by that time that no one could keep track of them. Through his periodical, Nezavisimyi rabochii vestnik ( Independent Worker's Herald), Dashkevich maintained contact with those trade unions and published a field guide to them, making it possible for their leaders to contact one another and seek ways to create a united labor front in Saint Petersburg.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Igor Aleksandrovich Dashkevich include personal and biographical documents, correspondence, and published and unpublished manuscripts. The collection, through memoirs, interviews, samizdat publications, and other materials collected by Dashkevich, documents the changing nature of samizdat published during the final years of Soviet rule and the emergence of an independent press with a wealth of publications on dissident life in Leningrad in the 1980s.
The collection also includes information on workers' protests in the early 1990s, including the Saint Petersburg teachers' strikes (1991 to 1992). Another side of Dashkevich's activity is seen in the materials relating to the Rubicon Library, as he attempted to document the newly burgeoning free press and publications by independent organizations and preserve their printed material in Western libraries. The latest documents in the collection relate to Dashkevich's arrest for participating in political protests in 2007.
Whenever possible, the original folder titles given by the creator have been maintained (in transliterated Russian on the physical folders, translated into English in this guide). Within individual folders, materials have been kept in their original order as accumulated by the creator.
Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Labor movement--Russia (Federation); Journalism--Soviet Union.; Journalism--Russia (Federation); Journalists.
- File 1: Paragraf, samizdat magazine layout, No. 9, 1989 April (Box-folder 1: 1-3)
- File 2: Revol't Pimenov writings, 1988-1990
  - "Bor'ba za konstitutsiiu," typescript, samizdat, Syktyvkar, 1988 (Box-folder 1: 4-5)
  - "Odin politicheskii process," typescript, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 6-7)
- Files 3-4: KLIO, samizdat magazine layouts, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 1: 8-10, 2: 1-2)
- File 5: NeRV, Nezavisimyi rabochii vestnik, Nos. 1-38, St. Petersburg, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 3-7)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes "Spravochnik po novym rabochim i profsoiuznym organizatsiiam g. Peterburga."
- File 6: Nikolai Ivanovskii writings, typescripts, circa 1980
  - "Bylo, da byl'em poroslo..." (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - "Svobodu vy liubite, svobodoi dorozhite" (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - "Egorka" (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - "Na nei krasivyi shelk" (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - "Vashei mame ziat' ne nuzhen?" (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - "Pogoda glupaia...dozhd'" (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Petushok" (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - "Dal'she solntsa ne ugoniat" (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - "Tri pis'ma" (Box-folder 3: 4)
- File 7: Aleksandr Suetnov writings, typescripts, 2001-2002
  - "Shpargalka dlia istorika,", 2002 (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
  - "Irrevoliutsiia: zapiski o Rossiiskoi smute,", 2001 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- File 8: Elena Nikolaevna Strukova, 1989-2002
  - "Analiticheskaia periodicheskaia pechat' i ee rol' v stanovlenii mnogopartiinosti v Rossii (1987-1996)," dissertation, 2002 (Box-folder 3: 8-9)
    Includes research material.
  - Photographs, notes, and drawings, circa 1989-2000 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    Includes photographs depicting Dashkevich.
- File 9: I. Konstantinov, K. Davydov-Tishchenko, A. Ulanov, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 3: 11-12)
  Includes writings, research material, and correspondence.
- File 10: Vladimir Bol'shakov writings, 1992-2002 (Box-folder 4: 1-2)
- File 11: Writings by Arsen'ev and others, typescripts, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 4: 3-4)
- File 12: Accounting and correspondence of NeRV and Rubikon newspaper editorial board and KLIO fund, 1990-2004 (Box-folder 4: 5-8)
- File 13: Samizdat, 1950-1980
  - "Kogda ia vernus'," by Aleksandr Galich, photocopy, circa 1980 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - "Evreiskoe dazibao (Jewish Dazibao)," by Igor' Guberman, typescript, 1980 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Photographs, 1950-1980 (Box-folder 4: 11-12)
    Includes photographs of A. Galich, B. Pasternak, V. Vysotskii, A. Solzhenitsyn, J. Brodsky, B. Okudzhava, and others.
- File 14: Igor Dashkevich writings, typescripts, 1985-1992 (Box-folder 5: 1)
- File 15: Igor Dashkevich projects of different years, 1980-2003 (Box-folder 5: 2-4)
- File 16: Tres Dias, 2002-2004 (Box-folder 5: 5-7)
  Includes photographs, list of followers, and printed matter relating to Dashkevich's fundraising activities at the St. Petersburg branch of the Tres Dias international Christian organization.
- File 17: RAFPROFIO, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 5: 8-9)
  Includes the Russko-Amerikanskii Fond Profsoiuznykh Issledovanii i Obucheniia (RAFPROFIO) (Russian American Foundation for Trade-Union Research & Education) program, reports, and memoranda.
- Files 18-19: Rubicon Library, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 5: 10, 6: 1-3)
  Includes correspondence, shipping lists, invoices, and other materials relating to the independent library at Rubikon (Magazin für die kritische Masse) and its international business collaboration with other libraries and archives.
- File 20: Helsinki University Library, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  Includes shipping lists and correspondence.
- File 21: USA, Professor Frederick Van Doren, 1990 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  Includes correspondence, orders, and shipping lists.
- File 22: Canada, The University of British Columbia, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 6: 6)
- File 23: Columbia University, Evgenii Beshenkovski, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  Includes invoices.
- File 24: Source materials for Rubikon, 1993-1997 (Box-folder 6: 8-10)
  Includes writings, notes, correspondence, and clippings.
- File 25: Miscellany, 2004-2007 (Box-folder 6: 11-12)
  Includes materials relating to Dashkevich's administrative infraction for his participation in political activities.
- File 26: University, 1977-2004 (Box-folder 6: 13-14, 7: 1-2)
  Includes materials relating to Dashkevich's study at St. Petersburg University.
- File 27: Igor Dashkevich, life, 1956-2008
  Includes biographical materials documenting Dashkevich's life.
  - Biographical file, 1978-1990 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    Includes passport, driving license, marriage certificate, and biographical note by Dashkevich's mother.
  - Education file, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    Includes educational activities award certificates. See also: File 26: University.
  - Writings, 1978-1984 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    Includes recollections on the Riabov trial in St. Petersburg.
  - Photographs, 1956-2008 (Box-folder 7: 6-10)
    Includes photographs depicting Dashkevich, his family, and friends.
- File 28: Correspondence, 1982-2007
  - General, 1982-2003 (Box-folder 7: 11)
    Includes correspondence relating to independent press publishing and distribution.
  - Purto, Victoria (Dashkevich's mother), 1986-2007 (Box-folder 7: 12-14)
- File 29: Immigration, 1973-1983 (Box-folder 7: 15-16)
  Includes correspondence, appeals, statements, and other materials relating to the immigration of the Dashkevich-Purto family.